presented by policy
[Music]
Bazar CNBC tv80 the policy Bazar
Insurance
show it is that time of the year when
you're all ready to take that
international trip which you've planned
and have been saving up for all year
long but have you planned your trip well
flight tickets booked hotel reservations
done Visa Arrangements done sightseeings
booked Forex arranged but what about
your travel insurance well if you've
already purchased the travel insurance
policy or are about to then today's
episode of the policy Bazar Insurance
show is for you we joined by Ashish Siti
president and head spu and travel at baj
alian General insurance and Anand singi
Chief retail and government business at
IC ICI Lombard to answer all your doubts
on how you can plan a stressfree travel
with a comprehensive travel insurance
plan thank you gentlemen for taking the
time out and speaking to us and sharing
your wisdom on this very very important
topic and more importantly at such a
relevant time Ashish first question to
you to speak about travel insurance
largely uh it is considered as the last
priority and just a checkpoint when it
comes to getting your visas how big of a
mistake or an error uh can that prove to
be and second what defines a
comprehensive travel insurance plan well
firstly Ash is a pleasure to be here and
thank you for having us and like you
said there's no better time as of now to
look at Travel Insurance because this we
are the cusp of uh or the annual of the
travel insurance season and uh with most
tickets being done and hotels being
booked and you know iter is being
chocked out ever so often people forget
to do the most important thing is buy
insurance that is the one aspect that
can turn the entire travel on its head
and it's extrud important to ensure that
we have looked at it in its minutest
detail because having a cover may not
cover what you requisitely required to
be covered so there is no comprehensive
insurance there is no comprehensive
insurance plan it's a modularity plan so
depending on the kind of travel that
you're doing you need to build and stack
up that plan so just to sort of
culminate it you look at your travel in
the sense of ensuring you look at the
best hotel you book the best airline you
book the best seat you even go to the
details of ensuring that you book the
best plan in terms of your food but ever
so often people don't look at the
insurance with the minutest eye and
that's what I would request people to
look at okay uh an to you if I could
pass on the same question but little
differently uh how big of a mistake can
it pro to be if you don't have uh a good
uh travel insurance plan while you're
traveling abroad what are those Min new
things the smaller things the bigger
things that one Should Be watchful of
while buying a travel insurance plan
there was a point in time when travel
insurance was primarily being bought for
visa requirements because a lot of
embassies would kind of want to have the
travel insurance so that your Visa is
processed properly but over the years
people have realized that travel
insurance in itself serves a very
significant purpose if you look at a
country right there are predominantly
almost like more than 3.3 craw people
traveling internationally every single
year and when we see what are the
categories of traveler we we kind of
really have them in four goots the the
ones to begin with are the early
Travelers who would possibly traveling
for the first or second time of their
life then you have more frequent
Travelers which are like zipping around
multiple times in a particular year
across the globe okay in that cohort now
there's a new section which is getting
developed which is the modern Travelers
which are the ones which are seeking
more fun also while they're traveling so
for like what Ashish mentioned people
who love doing adventure sports so on
and so forth correct and then there is a
very large category which gets unserved
is the senior citizen Travelers what is
the most relevant thing they should kind
ofly purchase in their travel insurance
plan is is going to be the defining
Factor so for example if there is
somebody who is traveling multiple times
during the year
he might prefer to go in for a multi-rip
travel insurance policy while if there
is a modern traveler who loves to kind
of really take a car on self ride or or
kind of really do some of adventure
activities he or she would need to plan
for the covers accordingly so what our
recommendation obviously is identify
what you want to do during your travel
and then select the necessary covers so
that you are completely and
comprehensively covered Ashish policies
have evolved the the purpose which they
serve has evolved but the thinking
largely even today in the minds of
policy holders is that a travel
insurance policy The Limited role is
that if there is a medical emergency
only in that case is when a travel
insurance policy comes to use but it
does so many things right I was just
reading about a few things flight
cancellations baggage theft and so many
more things which are associated with
your travel if a person's understood the
roles the multi-dimensional role which a
policy can cover uh does he have to ask
uh these additional roles as Riders to
the base policy or do standard policies
also come with these different roles
that are travel insurance can play yes
I'll answer that question but before
that it's important to understand that
everything being said and done the
penetration of travel insurance in this
country is just 30% so there's 70% of
Travelers who are not alluding to travel
insurance that itself is a massive risk
when they step out so that's at a 30,000
ft level now you s
granulizer say the 30% of the people who
are buying Insurance there's a lot of
modularity to the products so there is a
base cover but with Innovation and
digitalization there's a lot more that a
person can look at when he's traveling
for example there's a trip curtailment
there's a Car Hire so there are massive
number of add-ons so we for example have
42 add-ons and those 42 add-ons cover
everything so even from a senior citizen
cover for even waver of sublimit in
terms of a senior citizen cover you even
have your trip curtailment like I said
earlier on you have a flight delays you
have your overbooking cancellations you
have a lounge facility being provided if
you take that add-on cover so there's no
end to the covers that you like to have
but having said that it's important that
you look at the basic covers depending
on the kind of travel you're going to be
looking at people uh who generally are
you know uh going for business travels
and are frequent Flyers uh do they get
any kind of policy which covers them not
for one uh individual travel but for you
know certain number of years uh which
could be termed as long-term uh second
thing if yes what are the advantages of
buying a long-term policy versus buying
a policy every time I travel for
business or for a frequent visit that
I'm planning to make most insurance
companies have something called an
annual multi-rip uh travel insurance
okay and that basically covers you for
the number of trips that you would do
you don't have to go and buy one every
time you are traveling abroad a it's
expensive to buy it every time you go
Visa buying the annual multi-rip policy
B in some instances you may just forget
to buy it and then you at risk
unknowingly so that covers you for that
unknown risk also now on the multi-rip
there are some uh you know technical
aspects that one needs to consider you
should cover for all your gadgets
because they're important to you during
your business business travel B uh most
policies have a cover of up to 60 days
in a particular City and that's to be
known because if you're going to exceed
60 days you need to buy a temporary
extension policy right and there are
some products you know without naming
insurance companies where you have you
know uh extension of cover up to 180
days so those elements you need to keep
in mind in terms of the business travel
uh policies having said that like I
mentioned earlier if you look at the
other aspects of travel insurance there
those also get covered in the multi-rip
policy okay important is to look at the
duration the frequency and which part of
the world you're traveling to and ensure
that you have the adequate cover for
those regions but these are just for one
year purpose I mean multiple trip during
one year during one year you don't have
anything beyond one year right now in
the industry 2 years 3 years there those
options are also available they on the
anual but right now it's an annual
multi-rip policy okay but if I so I just
add across to what Ashish mentioned
mentioned there's another bit of
innovation which is taken the market
during the multi-rip policies you could
also choose the number of days for which
you would typically want to have the
policy being designed okay so for an
example you say that during the annual
multi policy I would want myself to be
insured for 90 days right and in case
for whatever reason you you could not
complete your 90 days there Provisions
which are being now kind of built across
where you could carry forward the number
on expire days of uh of you not using
the insurance polic it's pay as you use
so it's pay as you use I think so that's
one interesting which is taking shape an
I want to focus a little bit on a
different section of population as well
you know uh besides uh education besides
travel uh there are a lot of Indians who
are traveling uh maybe for a much longer
time to another country be it in search
of employment or any other reason right
if let's say a particular period has
been uh thought through uh by which the
person expects to get a job if that does
not happen What should he uh you know do
how should he you know have a health
insurance policy rather uh on in in any
other country in that sense what's the
real purpose of a travel insurance
policy it's fundamentally designed for
people who are traveling for uh business
purpose for uh let's say exploration
travel set of purpose and then kind of
really want to come back to the country
is it designed to take care of people
who are moving to another country for
residency purpose the answer is no okay
but yes there is time period to through
which you can kind of get your residency
uh kind of fixated in that particular
set of country so what typically the
travel insurance policies would do it
would cover you for 30 to 90 days at
times there are few setups at which you
can extend it to 120 days but besides
that if the condition or if the core
requirement is to kind of have a policy
which takes care of a residency in that
particular country uh we would urge our
viewers and travelers to kind of really
look out for an appropriate travel
insurance cover in the country where
they want to reside look at various
scenarios conditions companies and then
kind of choose the best possible cover
uh that's a very important point but on
that note uh it's time for us to take a
very very short break the journey
towards understanding travel insurance
continues on the other side of this very
small
break CNBC tv80 the policy Bazar
Insurance
[Music]
show welcome back to the policy Bazar
Insurance show we continue our disc
discussion on a very interesting topic
role of a comprehensive travel insurance
plan for a stress-free travel uh and
Anan to start the segment with you uh
you know both of you have been talking
so much about you know the the emergence
of adventure activities during every
travel now uh possibly even if the sole
purpose is not Adventure there is some
element of Adventure or activities
related to Adventure in every sort of
international vacation travel uh or
leisure travel uh which you make uh
while buying a travel insurance plan uh
does one have to be mindful of the fact
that you do let the insurance company
know that this could be a part of my
itinerary in whatever extent uh and if
yes is there sort of any additional
premium that you have to pay or does
this does this now because it's uh so
prevalent comes with the base policy
that you get while the person is
traveling abroad I think one should be
significantly mindful about what all
activities he would love to do in the
country in the new set of country which
he's traveling if there are activities
which are already planned in context to
Adventure Sports so for example if you
want to really go for a great hike do
some bit of trekking or indulge into
water sports and so on so forth uh we
would we would request our customers to
kind of declare that and also kind of
buy a rider or a plan which kind of
really uh covers the particular
individual for these set of activities
Ashish one question to you uh as we also
spoke about the fact that you know the
cost of getting medical attention be for
a longer time or relatively shorter time
uh like an OPD cover uh is still very
high in a lot of geographies otherwise
how does one go about looking at that
side of travel insurance if there is uh
uh let's say the requirement uh to get
some shorter medical attention and if
that claim is taken how does it impact
your suers Shard or the travel cover for
the balance part of your trip once that
has been taken care of at the core of it
it is a health insurance when you're
traveling abroad which entails a sum
insur hypothetically the sum insured is
$100,000 and say there's an OPD expense
of $5,000 with a deductible right
whatever that deductible may
be if there is a utilization of that OPD
that OPD gets reduced from your total
sum insured okay so for the balanced
tenure of your trip or visit you would
have a
$95,000 cover so that's the way it
operates it doesn't operate in silos
it's one cover one summ insur being
utilized by two elements which is OPD
and ipd Anan one question to you and
this is a serious problem as I look
through it uh most of us uh when we
travel uh you know internationally
largely the trips are booked by uh a
travel agent right while you know giving
you the requirements that you would need
for your Visa uh there is never been a
casee uh at least with me that the
travel agent is asked what are the
pre-existing ailments or diseases that
you have for the purpose of that travel
insurance policy which he's going to
issue to you is there a big risk when it
comes to claims if anything happens with
respect to and around those diseases
that they already have absolutely so
again yes Ashish had mentioned a very
critical point U stating that only 30
35% of the total Travelers in our
country were going out or taking us or
seeking a travel insurance policy uh one
of the reason while not in totality but
one of the biggest reason why people uh
there was significant amount of under
insurance or not being insured was
because of the fact that when people had
PD they had no option because most of
the insurance companies were not ready
to give covers for people who were kind
of Le covering with getting had PD with
them and essentially uh what happened
was disclosures around this fact was
significantly reduced what most of the
companies now have done is they have
great disclosure forms where the
customers or the viewers I think who who
is traveling they can kind of disclose
that they have got a pre-existing
disease they can communicate very
categorically what is the pre-existing
disease and the insurance companies
would take a note of it and then kind of
stitch in the covers which takes care of
you even if you have a pre-existing
disease and if you're traveling outside
outside the set of country so from uh my
own as well as the organization
perspective we would very strongly urge
that The Travelers should disclose uh
very very categorically if they have a
pre-existing disease Ashish if I could
ask you another question with travel
insurance how does one understand that
this is the right kind of cover that I
have to carry in case of any emergency
well there are multiple aspects that are
sort of looked at when you derive a su
insur but it's important to leave it to
the experts let the experts derive it
for you you need to trust in those
experts ever so often one wants to cut
down on the premium and therefore you
look at cutting down on the sum insured
if you're traveling to the US where you
know medical expenses are exorbitant
like I said earlier if you're going to
take a $100,000 cover or $200,000 C is
going to be significantly insufficient
if there's a
severity of sort of disease that
emanates over there number two it's
important to look at where you're
traveling and what you're doing so you
evaluate that but leave it to the
experts the experts will sort of derive
the right sumon short for you trust in
those experts and buy it Anand to speak
about you know the claims process in the
situation of a medical emergency how
does it flow through uh when you're
getting admitted to a hospital overseas
uh do you get admitted and let the
hospital you know intimate the insurer
back in India and handle the claims
process or do you or your family members
or your friends have to do the needful
of letting the insurer in India know
that there has been an admission and
this needs to be coordinated with the
hospital it all depends on the situation
out there if you are into a position
where you could intimate to the
insurance company it's always the best
because in that particular scenario the
cashless benefits can be extended to the
to The Travelers and the insurance
company would lien across with the
hospitals or the network providers in
the particular country and then ensure
that you have a smooth process which
kind of really is taken care of at the
back end in scenarios and in cases where
the Travelers have not been able to
intimate to the insurance companies and
they paid the medical treatment cost out
of their own inside of pockets then they
could kind of really intimate to the
insurance companies when they come back
to the country uh ensure that the
necessary documents are provided there
are some bit of formalities around there
where the insurers might have to reach
out to the hospitals to authenticate the
documents which are being provided
across and it might lead to a little bit
of DeLay So the best case scenario is uh
while there is option of reimbursement
which is always available is to to
intimate the insurance company by self
or any of your family members that there
is a medical emergency and there is a
treatment which is required in that
particular of country and the insurance
company would completely Li in out makes
sense uh before we conclude this episode
uh I would want to sort of get your
views on two individual topics one by
one to start with you Ashish the first
one and that section of the population
uh if you're traveling with senior
citizens or infants at the same time
both sides the risks would be very
different if the risks are different of
course the summer short or the cover
would be different yeah first let's just
what is a senior citizen what is a child
cover what are the age limits for that
so for senior citizen is 60 and above
okay and for children it is up to 21
right that being said for the senior
citizen cover like we discussed earlier
it's important to dulge all the
pre-existing diseases because your cover
would be determined by the pre-existing
diseases that you have right that's
Point number one point number two is
important to ensure that the senior
citizen has the information to support
the underwriting for that cover
proactively given to the underwriters so
that is determined in full format for
children I think it's important to look
at the adventure sports cover because
ever so often it's the children who
decide to sort of indul indulge to
sporting activities like you know
hangliding or you know water surfing and
so on scuba diving and it's important to
have that cover so I think not
withstanding these two most of the
addons would cover everything else okay
to you Anan a different section but I
want to focus a little on students uh
going in uh you know a different country
to pursue your higher education the
course could be a year long two years 3
years in that case is it advisable or
for him to buy an insurance policy from
an insurer of that country uh or can he
sort of rely on the health insurance
policy which he has back here in India
uh as I said for a period of 1 year 2
years 3 years most of the universities
would seek an insurance policy out of
India right and that's something which
is then provided to the students for the
tenure of the period for which you are
going to be studying in a in a different
set of country and it comprehensively
covers you for different kind of
scenarios for students specifically uh
there are add-ons which are available we
would always advise that the students
who are traveling out of the country to
check with the universities in in case
of whether the insurance company in
India should provide the policy or they
have a rule where they have to buy a
local uh local health insurance policy
okay thank you gentlemen for being here
today on CNBC tv18 and sparing the time
for this comprehensive discussion but uh
with that we come to an end to the
special episode of the policy Bazar
Insurance show remember the key
takeaways from today's discussion uh
know the geography know the place where
you're traveling and what kind of cover
travel insurance cover it would require
know the activities that you're
indulging in and do ask the insurer you
know to cover those activities all your
requirements and most importantly make
sure that you disclose all your
pre-existing diseases in advance so that
uh at the time of seeking a claim there
is no issue but with that uh we come to
an end to this episode we'll meet you
soon uh next week with a new episode
with another interesting topic till then
uh stay safe stay
insured cmbc tv80 the policy Bazar
Insurance
show presented by policy Bazar